all right welcome cohort 5 it's March
11th and Andrew thanks for taking us on
to chapter eight part two so go for
it all
right okay it's our second week on
chapter eight
um and just a brief refresher that this
chapter is in the second part of the
text book and so we're now focusing more
upon building our own models and getting
a sense of how to draw relationships
between phenomena of interest and how to
actually map them to variables in active
inference models chapter 7even we saw um
discrete State space models and so we
were looking at pdps and now chapter 8
now transitions to continuous State
space models which is sort of the the
found ation uh the starting point for uh
historically for developing active
inference models a lot of the earlier
work of uh frisen par and others was on
continuous models first um so here we're
looking at continuous State space models
which are well suited for modeling let's
say physical
fluctuations uh impinging on sensory
receptors and for the continuous motion
of the ectors or muscles we use to
change the world around us is a quote
from the chapter um here we have model
examples for dynamical systems involved
in motor control as well as the concept
of generalized synchrony with the bird
song example and finally constructing
Hybrid models uh near the end which
would actually combine discrete and
continuous variables um so it kind of
almost add mixture of what we confronted
in chapter 7 now with continuous
variables being situated as well for
example at a lower level of the model um
since it's our second week uh from there
I think we could just jump in does
anyone have any thoughts uh on this
chapter any questions anything they're
they're still kind of uh crunching
through uh in their mind about about how
a lot of this
works
[Music]
all I'll at one point thank you Andrew
for the quick opening I think it's an
interesting point that like you said it
was
initially uh with the earlier FR and Par
models in continuous time and now the
continuous time is being Revisited in
the basy mechanic setting so it's kind
of like a purely dynamical
systems
justification which is very similar to
the SPM textbook so kind of classical
equations of motion which kind of turns
out to be like the um classical
Newtonian basian
[Music]
mechanic so the kind of pre
uh continuous time which is where
most of the this chapter's
Focus um like including just the
differential
equations including the
chaotic deterministic systems that's
just the kind of pure dynamical
systems approach again very similar to
SPM and then this textbook doesn't
really go into basing mechanics because
this textbook was published March 2022
so probably was written um
between First's
2019 free energy principle for a
particular physics and then obviously
the book being published in
so it's
mentioned
but many of the works that that
made it clearer are only after the book
just to kind of give a little more
context on the continuous
time
yeah so we start with continuous we move
to discreet and now we're back to
continuous but it's kind of using what's
been developed since then and also being
able to yeah combine the two um as
well
yeah in the the nested hybrid model at
the end of chapter 8 is basically like
picked up on by this
paper which we discussed in live stream
46 and they basically pick up on that
exact hybrid model I don't know if they
use a
figure let's see the hybrid
86 on page 166 oh sorry sorry yeah yeah
you're looking at the paper yeah just
that but I don't know they didn't
include it there but
uh
here yeah figure 8.6 so here continuous
time on the bottom
because of the D
derivatives and then discrete time on
the top because of the transition Matrix
and the explicit
time and then in this paper they say
okay with a belief desire intention like
BDI model including discussion of like
whether that is f psychology etc etc but
within that commonly used like can you
talk about beliefs desires and
intentions and all these
things they it it's not that it does
better or any different even per se it
just it's non-contradictory
so that's kind of an interesting first
way to put
it hey
oi is that particular paper does it
discuss much
like well I'm not sure how deeply you
want to go into that or maybe another
example but it it seems like a maybe a
nice way of like finding um for week two
here like um another application of what
we find in chapter 8
like what's what's going on in that
paper as far as like
distinguishing discreet from continuous
variables to have a recollection of like
the model set up there
let's look at another time but I think
they all they mainly explored like
differences in the belief desire
intention map into the model and not
sure how much they focused on that
sensory motor part but yeah gotta
sure yeah BR uh yes uh sorry uh could
you please go to that uh sorry that
desire part which they're mentioning uh
in that paper the desire thing yeah can
you please spend some time on
this yeah I think in
the you noticed it in the um the figure
probably see yeah D AI they're using for
discreet and that um
M AI I think for motor
AI so here they're looking at the um C
preference
distribution which is a distribution
over
observables and then um contrasting the
observation of tasting ice cream and not
tasting ice
cream so these two um alternative ways
you could parameterize that like in a
program or an equation here's 7.3 like a
coin flip 7.3 70% of the time I expect
to be tasting ice cream here it's 99%
expecting to be tasting ice
cream so then that c is
stronger and so it entails a stronger
motivational Force Through pragmatic
value in
E so that's one way to kind of look at
it and then there's the other the way
that the textbook kind of talked about
it is with the c
scaling but so depending on the program
sometimes you're working in the scaled
c um or unscaled scaled meaning to the
statistical distribution or like here so
that here Ice Cream versus no is being
described summing to one like a coin
flip like a real
distribution so then you get
99999999999
or that could be represented as like 1
million to
one so just depends on exact situation
whether you're working in the kind of
setting where you can learn by counting
through experience or do other
modifications and then when that's used
as a distribution for pragmatic value
it's transformed into something sus to
one could you please send a link to this
p paper uh in the chat
box yeah it'll just be on the chapter 8
page yeah I'll put there
too yeah so if there are no
um anyone please feel free to bring up
any other questions you might have along
the way or you know toggle the reaction
to raise your hand
um but so in in this chapter along the
way we're we're introduced to things
like
attractors um we're introduced as well
to the concept of generalized synchrony
comes up a bit later
um and that's a particular notion that
um you know as we know active inference
agents are attempting to model the
hidden States uh of the environment so
they're attempting to model their
environment what's going going on around
them generaliz synchrony is this notion
that
um that the agent is basically their
internal states are modeling or in
certain ways beginning to synchronize
with um the states around them we have
no proof of course like the agent itself
has no
pure objective proof that it's somehow
perfectly understanding the environment
and all variables around it but
nonetheless there's a kind of
synchronizing going on and this can be
applied to a kind of multi-agent setting
and so here uh later on on in the
chapter we're given this like bird song
example which um you know the textbook
is published in 2022 but the brid song
example goes back
to um at least
2015 potentially sooner um but the there
are a couple 2015 papers by friston and
Par where basically
investigating using continuous
variables um they
simulate uh two song birds singing songs
right and what they do is that um
there's a we start to see this kind of
emergent phenomena of course with with
active inference models one of the big
uh aims here of doing modeling is to
like set up your variables set up your
model run a simulation and then see what
kind of emergent phenomena arise with
the bird s song example
they first um set up two birds that have
identical models so not to not too uh
surprising to find okay they have
identical models they have the two song
birds like quote unquote within earshot
like they can the two song birds have
actions where they can sing and then
they can take in sensory observations
that being of continuous auditory
signals and so it's like the bird
are singing to each other and listening
to each other the emergent phenomena
that begins to happen is we start to see
them taking turns it's as if they're
singing from the same hym sheet or the
same
script um and the generalized synchrony
interestingly even occurs whenever they
set up the model um the the simulation a
second time around where the birds
actually have different starting models
so the birds start in different spots as
far as their like State space like
coordinates
go and over time the bird's models
actually begin through perceptual
learning uh to to mirror one another so
even though we start off with two
different agents they start to
synchronize um now they're singing the
same him sheet again even though they're
two you know very different birds as far
as starting points go
um the way that's modeled is through
using attractors and La system and so uh
in this case there's something that's
called like a a synchronization of chaos
which is rather interesting because you
know with a chaotic system if you have
two chaotic systems presumably they're
you know even if you put them at the
same starting point um their
trajectories will very quickly diverge
um you know with INF infin
infinitesimally small chance that they
will just magically line up but whenever
you have two agents who are able to act
um and
listen uh to one another and they start
to do this thing where they're following
the same Hy sheet suddenly you have a
kind of synchronization of these two
chaotic systems and we see those kinds
of um Dynamics Illustrated in the in the
chapter is kind of orbiting in figures
8.4 and
8.5 and um
so yeah kind of a a lining up between
different agents I think it's
interesting for anyone who's curious
about trying to set up systems or do
multi-agent settings where they're
trying to see you know how a joint
action begins to play out between agents
saying uh how agents can work together
to um
ultimately minimize their own distinct
you know free energy
um but by in order to do that they
actually have to like yeah entrainment
is a good word like one of them entrains
the other um so that they can stay on
the same page minimize prediction errors
and it's fascinating because the there
are all kinds of uh Rich behaviors and
dynamics that that occur um like the the
the songs that are being sung presumably
they like vocal Glides and brief pauses
and so it's not just you know super
simple Behavior that's that's being
synchronized here but nonetheless it
occurs
see
the bird song also I I like how this
chapter brings up oh uh Peres is that
your hand up again uh yeah sorry I have
a I may be wrong actually but just
correct me um so for synchrony there
needs to be some kind of a coupling uh
I'm just wondering is it anywh Ed with
the generative process and the
generative models like the act like we
have the like the Gen process is in a
way uh complementary to the generative
model is it possible that that plays an
impact sure so so in this
example there's not too much going on in
terms of U so just as a starting point
so with modeling you're going to be
defining a generative model and you're
going to be defining a generative
process in this example there's not too
much distinct going on whenever a
generative process is defined in fact
here it's like we have two generative
models so two
agents and they're coming into contact
with each other so it's like for bird
number one
its model is itself um its process that
it's coming into contact with is just
the other bird so you can think about
the the observations that bird number
one is taking in they're all being
generated by by bird number two um as
part of the the environment the process
that's around it um does that make
sense I think you you're right I think
instead of thinking terms of a
generative process Alto together like
two different agents and they have like
uh uh similar kind of internal model and
uh and that is kind of causing kind of
some kind of a coupling mechanism and so
over a long period of time uh they may
start to have behaviors which are
similar to each other no like you
mentioned that him sheet right so one
person may say the starting lines and
then then after sometime the second
person will say the second thing then
the third will say first will say the
third and like that observations might
happen yeah it's like the pendulum
example which I think uh was mentioned
last week like we have these two
pendulums which are swinging and over a
very very long period of time they'll
they'll kind of um oscillate together no
yeah yeah know that's exactly right and
uh that's that's also referenced in the
bird song paper so yeah just basically
being able to start two different in
that yeah in that case your pendulums
are kind of like your agents um and yeah
via you know via physics via the the the
general logic that we're looking at here
of like attractors yeah they begin to
kind of move towards attracting points
but they're acting as each other's
attracting points so to speak um such
that yeah their their behaviors start to
to synchronize and so with the the birds
the bird song is an interesting example
versus the pendulums because the
pendulums they just like continue moving
for the birds um we have this
turn-taking Dynamic that begins to occur
because the the birds are trying to in
terms of you know act act of inference
and the free energy principle they're
actively Trying to minimize their
prediction error and the way they do
that here is that they want to hear a
song like they want to take
in uh sensory observations that show
that are realizing the preference of
hearing a a song and the two ways they
can do that that of course our
perception changing their mind their own
mind or uh action which is changing the
world and so this turnt taking Dynamic
involves a combination of sensory
attention and sensory
attenuation uh is how it's phrased here
and these are also um interesting
mechanics that we find in in just about
any active inference model where action
is involved um you have to so the birds
take turns because like how do you keep
a song going well one uh you need to
hear that it's going on so they
attenuate or or kind of like pause um
their
um their incoming sensory
signals uh to uh commit actions that
realize hearing the song it's like oh I
don't hear a song I need to sing that's
that's realizing my preference um okay
I've sung um now I
pause I hear the other bird singing I
take that in as a sensory signal the
other bird uh begins to
sing maybe it sings notes that I expect
great maybe it sings notes that I don't
now we have prediction error starting to
to jump up yeah and so whenever that
happens of course the bird number one
has to minimize its prediction error and
so it starts to sing itself again and
because these two birds are basically
doing this back and forth there's a kind
of synchrony where they're because
they're both trying to minimize the
prediction error the way that they sing
the actions that they take the specific
ways that they sing um like they start
to synchronize they start to to match
notes start matching expectations and
that's the kind of thing that we see
playing out in the the graphs um and the
figures in the in the and the textbook
um especially figure
8.5 on the right the authors here you
know frisen and everyone they're trying
to show uh like a before learning and
after learning for these two birds on
the left- hand side it's like okay these
are the these are the Dynamics playing
out here are the here are the dynamical
equations um and then on the right you
can see the upper graph before learning
these are kind of like the state spaces
of each Bird's expectations they're they
top- down predictions um they're a
little bit more all over the place
whenever they start they begin to
synchronize so that you know whenever
whenever bird want and recall these are
continuous um State spaces which is why
we are able to do this as coordinates
rather than having to look at like
discreet um you know Point masses or
something um so where bird number one's
uh or excuse me yeah the first Bird's
expectations in that lower right graph
whenever they're around 10 um you know
whenever we whenever we plot them um the
second Bird's expectations are also
around a value of 10 whenever bird
number one's uh expectations or
predictions are around 50 same case for
the second bird so that's that's what
they're trying to get at with these
graphs is yeah they begin to the
expectation even though they're
dynamically shifting around we're never
always at zero we could be at 50 this
moment we could be at5 this moment um
the the important point is that the
first Bird's predictions and the second
Bird's predictions are um basically both
lining up at just about any given
moment one one interesting thing I
hadn't seen or before was like here it's
going between
at least
60 but here it's only going to
40 yeah
presumably I mean we have before
learning and after learning so
presumably they maybe just before
learning haven't explored quite as much
of the this state space yet right like
we have this much more EXP
exploration after learning you've run
more you know trials or at least
extended the the time
Horizon and then here they are like
starting to syn up singing new notes
that they'd never sung before or however
you'd like to phrase that and yeah the
the scale starts expanding because
they're they're trying new
things not sure nice nice
interpretation yeah it's a it's it's a
thought in any case and I also noticed
it looks on the after learning graph it
it looks slightly more chaotic or just
messy not quite as synced up once you
get past 50 on the after learning my
guess is that like oh this is a new the
new terrain that they're exploring here
um yeah these little micro little micro
densities
yeah
so presumably after more trials like
we'll see an even
finer kind of line or syncing up what
happens between
them we should find the at lab it might
it may even be an
SPM
example there's also a kind of mini
Standalone
SPM like while it is a mat lab package
there's a a kind of like
compiled Standalone
SPM oi or or others people like it it
it's worth a a try yeah and the bird
song I I I I could check or we could
check together because it's kind of been
around long enough to probably be
included in
the Dem
demo yeah actually that's that's right
um I was just having a look at the the
paper um I think I dropped in the chat
there but yeah just just about any of
these uh friston co-authored papers
prior at least prior to maybe the past
couple years it's like going to a paper
crlf SPM see if they you know have a
script there um that they're you know
they'll always mention in the paper of
course there you go and um yeah it looks
like it is in there
um yeah for For Better or Worse of
course matlb still requires um a license
to use but but I myself have downloaded
the the SPM Standalone before um you
just you know unfortunately of course
you cannot run M Matlab scripts if you
don't have Matlab so spm's nice as far
as like you get
this um this like graphical system all
of these different options of demos you
can click you can look at the graphical
outputs and yeah it looks like this
one um is included in there it's like
that um bird song
uncore um oh no dmore demoore d.m so it
can run M scripts in the background you
just can't hop in and access them and
modify them yourself uh to tweak the
parameters or anything like that
unfortunately but yeah it's nice it's
there there like literally dozens of of
preloaded scripts in there if you just
download the SPM Standalone you just
click one and uh you can you can watch
what kind of graphical outputs it comes
up
with yeah and we can also explore
bringing it into RX and F and
everything
yeah yeah
definitely
um and for anyone here who's not
familiar um The Institute has an ongoing
project Thursday mornings well sorry I'm
in the US some ADV to that but
um early on
Thursdays uh there's an RX infer project
for anyone who's interested in adapting
the the logic of active inference that
we're reading about here to direct
application in uh the Julia programming
language and um right now we're going
over different examples that are already
provided by the developers byas Labs uh
of this RX infer package um but um we'll
be expanding from there uh different
people you know are proposing their own
Community projects uh you know diff
different kinds of use cases are coming
up with and that we could try uh
emulating as a group uh and then another
focus is that we would like to be able
to reproduce some of these
existing uh um projects or or topics for
example here we could try and take the
take the mat lab script for the bird
song example and recreate it in Julia
and uh finally just final note um is the
um Julia programming language as well as
the way that bias laabs is developing
the RX infer package it's just it's nice
that it's it's using this
more um kind of sophisticated but also
highly
efficient method for the
computation uh and message passing as we
saw in the textbook back around chapter
5 um to to really just like being a ble
to scale up these kinds of processes and
and being able to just basically better
use your computational resources save on
some time um efficiency all that good
stuff we in the programming World care
about um yeah Francis you have your hand
up uh yeah I just wanted if there's uh
two questions actually firstly uh if
there's likely to be any support for a a
pmdp group because I'm already having to
Learn Python I I'm not I can't really
commit to learning a second programming
new programming language from scratch at
the same
time uh so I've been kind of slowly
working through the um that nice pmdp
tutorial um uh book Running it on the um
is it collab
uh and uh the other
question is
um is there anything to be leared or is
it not a really helpful
parallel uh between the idea of the bird
song example as a kind of autocomplete
and
how uh does it does active
inferences uh success
here compare it uh in any way to um
llms uh success
at uh GPT for the world's smartest AO
complete thanks just to quickly address
it so right now like we do not have any
active
PDP specific group we could we could do
a
similar kind of
thing right now the RX and fur is really
it's it is kind of interesting it's it's
um just from knowing PDP to medium
degree it is different
syntactically
however
like it
is it's very different and it's a more
General
than
pmdp in several ways not to say that
that that one can't have other you know
things the other doesn't
have but just the that um RX and
fur pulls way back like to the coin
flip which was really helpful and then
then builds up whereas PDP wraps it
focuses on just kind of getting you to
the discreet time active agent PDP as
fast as
possible because that's that's like not
every use case but that's
like many use cases and then it can kind
of be
modularized from there but RX and fur
is it's a it's a very promising
effort a lot broader so I I think it's a
good way to go I'm kind of excited to
learn it a lot ol is very good at
it other than the second piece about the
the um llms well
one we we um we haven't had a a streamer
discussion on with these authors but
this is one
interesting paper
recently um and then yeah like it's
almost like a question of what
what is perceived as a um Computing
Benchmark especially if other
considerations like interpretability or
energy it's
like is it a challenge is it a Computing
advance to open a larger file with a
computer with more RAM it's like yes but
maybe it's not proportionally or
differently a kind of
benchmark so then what what are
benchmarks for active
models and like or or even kind of in
another um setting like with the morph
stream with Sarah Hamburg different
guests it's been interesting to like
hear how they talk about like the
different characteristics of the biom
mtic Computing system
because they are not it's not simply
just like the
um CPU
[Music]
Ram
descriptions thanks so much that's it
looks like a really um interesting uh
paper
yeah and only six pages oh no comments
of six pages yes yeah it's a sure it's
definitely a starter so I and I think
that they and many other people are
interested and and a big um um like of
course the models are different if you
look at the Transformer
architecture um or um but but there's
some interesting with the state space
models like the
Mamba there's there's a few people like
Matt Perkowski who have um talked a
little bit about the relationship
between the stat spased models and
active inference so that may be actually
a closer relationship but um just in
terms of how the Transformers are
different than active inference models I
mean in the textbook
group chap these chapters are showing us
what the ACM model is you can then just
look at the Transformer architecture and
just see how they are different
architecturally but then um in in this
paper they kind of highlight this kind
of uh
ongoing there there's various aspects to
highlight there's the epistemic value
there's the
um reinforcement and but there's also a
lot of overlaps as these are just large
statistical
models
yeah oh thanks that's
great oh and this is another good one
where um they talk about how you in
active inference you can construct the
causal graph to be like that there is an
uncertainty parameter or like a
temperature parameter on some other
parameter or there's like introspective
access that using the um classic
Lars live stream 28 figures with the
meta awareness so if you construct the
model to be this way then this parameter
actually has that role in the system
whereas if you ask a prompt no matter
what you ask or how you ask it um to a a
Transformer
architecture and what is it like to be
you and all these kinds of questions
that people are very interested in it's
only ever giving that semantic
space fuzzy statistic of Words Answer so
it could say I'm very sure that it's
this way or very sure it's that way or
I'm not sure or I feel this way when
it's that way but those are all just
words generated from
texts um statistics of
texts so they will never approach an
actual
introspection so here they raised the
possibility of the actual
introspection that's very interesting a
totally different author list
uh is can we have that link on the um uh
encoder as
well thank you so
much this is all interesting with the
comparison to llms because I've been I'm
no expert on that topic but I've been
looking into it more myself and yeah
there is this kind of
um there's this kind of notion that okay
llms are great as far as um you know
kind of per performance goes with with
accuracy and um and all of the
computation there nonetheless yeah major
the kind of criticisms and the sort of
um debate or contrasting between llms
and actm is just more generally like oh
it takes a ton of computational
resources to train in llm and then once
you're kind of finished training it it's
like okay well there it is it's not a
it's not conceived as an agent who's um
who's able to engage in action uh right
so like try and it it's like to the idea
would be you'd have to have an llm that
had the capacity to actually go and
explore information itself and then
presumably it' have you know from an
active inference uh take it would have
to have its own preferences of how to
you know that it wants to realize so to
speak or C Matrix in the or C vector and
the PDP scheme or however you would like
to think of it and um so it's it's the
it boils down to the idea that an llm is
passive um it can't go explore it can't
update information and new you know
expand its uh State space dynamically or
or do things that maybe u a more active
uh agent could um it's kind of like okay
well once you've trained it like that's
what you've got um nonetheless I'm very
curious about the paper that yeah share
because that looks like it it's it's
actually saying no llms are not entirely
passive but let's talk about
it yeah that that that's all true and
also what's really interesting though is
the um I mean what what we might call
ecosystems of shared intelligence or
just the multi-agent
prompting they like when you on
perplexity AI or on um any internet
enabled like cloud
provider um or even if even in the uh
local retrieval augmented
generation where it's like you have a
library of documents and then the it pre
um assembles into the context window
what's relevant like that's an
information
forging so this is kind of like um is it
active inference like low
road like has it been constructed
according to chapter
six using like forked code from an act
in Freo or is it just being described
as in in terms of having particular uh
States like figure uh uh 9.1 with the
kind of rat in the Maze like making a
cognitive model of another language
model that that doesn't mean it it will
be useful to do
that but the these models are prompting
each other in ways that makes them have
epistemic value like they do do web
searches even if
one language model locally doesn't have
certain properties so there's a lot of
um
interactions which is kind of only to be
expected and even these other these
systems are are basically multi-agent
models like like the large ones that are
closed
source
but not in the kind of spatial Mobility
way properly just like in the combining
inputs gotcha I was actually personally
not familiar with the fact that like
these are technically multi-agent setups
um that's really interesting and also
makes an imense amount of sense actually
um yeah yeah and they're working off of
one another another I'm not trying to
over relate but just given this is the
the textbook group of course it's like
a you know we have the bird song example
where the birds are trying to help each
other um so to speak uh not we can't
that's an interpretation to say that
they're trying to help each other but
the point being that they're both trying
to minimize their prediction errors and
so they're playing off of one another
sharing information with one another or
in this case a song guess with L llms in
a certain
sense of course them being constructed
very differently we're talking about
this right now but they're kind of
working off of one another to yeah yeah
I think another good uh point there in
the context of building the models is
like it's not necessarily about building
like one Megatron agent that has every
property it's about like what things are
there and
then starting to describe their
interfaces which are usually less
ambiguous and then describing the things
and and their interfaces and
interactions then maybe all you need is
a
oscillator versus like a lot of times
the kind of speculation about very very
Advanced kinds of models but as we're on
RX and
fur
like- which is awesome too the um the
the the philosophy far
outruns simple
models so depending on what we're really
trying to explore just you know
describing and then having and then
having the modularity of the model so we
could start with a
pendulum but then know that the
interface would be described like in a
stable way in RX and
fur so that would have made large
progress
towards different kinds of phenomena
without necessarily getting caught up in
trying to locate it too early in a given
architecture for a single
agent
can I do one more question does this
idea of
the uh
synchronization
um refer back to the phrase you used
earlier about was it community of
something a
shared something yeah yeah I think
here's here's a good citation okay good
this one's it was on archive for some
time then it was published here
here's the ecosystems of intelligence or
shared intelligence and this kind of
lays
out I guess other people can also give
their summaries I see it it doesn't make
any technical advances or descriptions
there's only one
figure um it's just laying out this idea
of the
interacting things through message
passing this is the
figure here's some manifold and then
belief
updating interesting reading
format and then um then they just talk
about how message passing amongst
diverse intelligences in ecosystems of
shared
intelligence that's kind of the frame
then they describe these um stages of
development
kind of an interesting read in terms
of their timelines the scriptures
[Music]
Etc wow yeah thank you very
much so it looks like in that paper
they're
describing uh like certain aspects of
one
agent's own
model act as points of
reference
for other agents and vice versa so that
you end up with this kind of like
Ecology of belief
sharing a kind of collective
intelligent intelligence resting on
shared narratives and goals
um again not to to
overrate everything here but with the
bird song example I had actually like I
this past week took some time to like
actually read that paper itself the bird
song One not just its briefer
description uh in the textbook and
there's a lot of there's a lot of
interesting things actually going on in
that 2015 bird song paper I in some ways
this might be just designing ecosystems
of intelligence from first principles
more than likely has some relationship
there because the bird song example it's
not just of course it's not just about
trying to talk
about distinctly birds and and song
birds and like you know uh as as
interesting as that could be from a a
biological or Zoological or otherwise
standpoint it's really trying to get at
something like how do
agents share information with one
another and kind of in Trin one another
how do we have how and why do we see
things like convergence of
beliefs um as far as biological
organisms go we can see a
synchronization of things beyond the
words um we can see like whenever two
people are talking to each other their
the rate of their speech tends to begin
to converge over time or or exhibit you
know near identical characteristics
um the kind of vocabulary that people
use tends to kind of sync over time as
well um and then yeah there's so there's
this kind of shared narrative a kind of
um you know from a seal agent
perspective uh the single agent is
starting to model um the behavior of the
world around it the process as well as
its own um two agents might start to
model each other and in a sense uh there
uh the bird song paper claims it's not
just that once you get to this
multi-agent setting where where the
agents are entraining one another and
starting to show identical behaviors and
internal model mappings and U modeling
of the world of each other uh it's not
just that they're modeling the other
Bird's Behavior or their own behavior
they phrase it as they're beginning to
like our Behavior like there's a kind of
collective behavior on the on the
horizon here that they're starting to
model um yeah I I just think that's a
very very interesting and potentially
one of the core aspects of trying to to
get into this kind of collective
intelligence synchronization kind of
logic here yeah
yeah great point I mean when it's on a
onedimensional manifold like in the
extreme case or even just as a heris
like if 80% of the variability is
captured by one number like you're on a
a one-dimensional manifold on the
two-dimensional space that's the that's
what a manifold is and then yeah you're
totally right this is not really a uh
it's not an Ornithology paper in the
traditional sense because it is about
hermeneutics and it is with this other
joint paper that they
reference that's like a a twin paper
and so it it's it's totally interesting
that it has a lot to do like you said
with
narrative and with uh
interpretation here they
um they take like a dynamical systems in
approach to
interpretation later that is also like
um expanded and complemented by the
quantum reference frame Chris
Field's syntax and semantics
work but this is like a a perception
action
grounded dynamical
hermeneutics so not addressing all
semantic or Semitic questions but that
but like how dynamical
systems can have General synchrony which
doesn't mean doing the same thing it can
mean it can mean Mutual information
increases
through
differences like or in um in the Chris
Fields setting like the the principle of
unitarity and like that systems um come
into entanglement with each other and
then that was discussed like does that
mean that they go to the same States
like no not
necessarily and I say as a counselor who
goes into conversations with people
where they know their world but maybe
they're stuck and I don't know their
world but I have models of how to get
unstuck
this
is uh
wow um very very very interesting thank
you yeah no super super interesting I
mean I think I I think there's enough to
go off of here at least theoretically
that potentially one of the key
um aspects
of Counseling and as well as other
things clinical therapy and so on is
that uh just basically a so-called
talking cure or some s some such thing
is for someone who's having uh kind of
repetitive uh you know behaviors or
thoughts or you know whether you want to
view them from a symptomatic perspective
in the cases of like I don't know
depressive rumination or a variety of
other kind of things that come up like
in one sense from an active inference
perspective it might be that someone is
having something
like difficulty with belief updating and
that by talking like actually just
talking with another human being um you
might see the person who's who's you
know the client you might start to see
them like you know not not to be too
theoretical or kind of philosophical
here but there's almost a kind of
potential s thinking to some degree of
what we might call their internal States
or their behaviors or otherwise with
that of the counselor or the the
therapist you know um whole different
set of questions and and research to be
done or research that's already been
done just try and claim like that that
can have a a long-term impact of course
like counseling or therapy like there
are regular sessions so you're getting
like repeated instances of these these
temporary sinking EP uh sinking Up
episodes going on and then another
aspect of course is that the counselor
and or therapist they don't want to
actually themselves imitate um the
behaviors being seen by the client they
want to help not match um but yeah just
you know just trying to extrapolate a
little bit here yeah that's why we have
a a fairly precise definition of empathy
as if we were feeling the same as our
client as if we were in their world but
not actually being in their
world I have to leave thank you so much
all right sure next
time fors chapter nine thank you Andrew
so see you all next time bye take care